Welcome to Business Central launch
edition 2026 release wave one and our
session about introduction in
withholding taxes. My name is Alexander
Totovich and I'm product manager uh for
business central team. So what is
withholding tax? And before I proceed
with withholding tax, I just want to
explain one thing. Withholding tax can
be applied to vendors to customers to
employees.
So this is related to many different
options. Uh but in this case currently
with this functionality we are covering
withholding taxes related to vendors and
purchase process. So this is what is
covered in this release. So withholding
tax is actually a tax deducted at source
from payment before the recipient
received the net amount. In the most of
cases it will be uh based on a payment
but it can happen to be on a invoice
when you uh create invoice or eventually
what is earliest but in most of cases
this on payment. So collect and limited
by payer on behalf of recipient. So
recipient is not someone who can decide
if they want to pay or do not want. This
is related by rules. So this is required
by law in many countries and you just
need to behave related to this law. It
applies to specific income types and
often this is uh based on some fixed
rate or threshold. So you will not pay
until some amount after that you need to
calculate. So there are a lot of these
specific information and we try to
deliver all of them into this uh new
functionality.
So how does it work? We have user. So we
are here as a customer as a user we have
our vendor we have authorities and we
have some setup where we decided for
example in this uh here that withholding
tax is 20%. So this is regulation. So
now we will receive invoice from vendor
in $1,500.
This is invoice and all good. But when I
need to pay it I will not pay the same
amount to our vendor. I will have
automatically I will start payment with
1500 but it will be recalculate and
actually payment for my vendor will go
as a 1200 and 300 will be paid directly
to authorities. So in general I will
close my invoice. I will close with
payment. I paid what is required but not
absolutely the same amount to my vendor
because I had to pay 20% of this amount
to my authorities. So this is how
withholding taxes are working in general
especially on vendor site. So to make it
how we started with the setting up we
wanted to apply if not the same but very
similar rules as we have in other uh
areas of v central. So what does it
mean? We have business posting groups we
have product posting groups. We have the
same for the general posting groups we
have for VAT. So we wanted to use the
same model here. So we have withholding
tax business posting group withholding
tax product posting group for all of
them together. We have withholding tax
posting setup. So this is how when we
cross two of them we have get a regular
setup. But when you start with
withholding tax posting setup you will
find another rules. They are not only
percentages you can find withholding tax
percentage but you have these threshold
rules. if they are less than less than
or equal equal greater greater than
equal so there are different rules you
can apply and as I said percent on top
on top of that and when you will realize
when you have uh released invoice or
payment on what is earliest so there are
basic setup you can find in withholding
tax posting setup but what else we have
there we have revenue type if you have
different revenue types you can you can
choose them you can set up and choose
very simple of a table but you have
sequence and what does it mean with
sequence? With a sequence you can have
more than one bit holding tax in the
same for same vendor for same uh model
in some situations. So you can set up a
se a sequence the system will first
calculate this one and then next one and
third one. So this is how this is order
how system will calculate one by one and
of course you have accounts the balance
accounts uh for setting apps where you
will post all this information.
So now I will show this in a demo how it
works and I will first start with
vendors to show that I enable this
vendors for withholding tax.
What does it mean? I need to invoicing
tab to enable withholding tax liable.
From this moment I will enable this
field withholding tax business uh
posting group and I have for these two
vendors. If I go to third you can see
this withholding tax busy posting group
is disabled. So you don't need to have
populated for all of them. So if
withholding tax alliable is not enabled
system will not require this posting
group for this vendor. But in a case
that I enabled uh withholding tax liable
for this vendor and I didn't populate
the withholding tax uh posting group
system will block posting for this
vendor because you do not have completed
setup. So I will not enable this type
this vendor. So I will use uh first two
vendors for my examples and let's start
with the purchase invoice.
Okay. I will uh yes I wanted to show you
before purchase invoice configuration on
items.
You have this option on items as well.
So you have on
withholding tax product posting group as
well. So I do not have configured them.
So no but you will see now I have for
this lamp I have withholding tax items
and I have for another one. So I have
for these two items configure a
withholding tax uh calculation
and um
be before I proceed there
I want to show withholding tax setup.
So I already have configure uh business
group,
product group. So I have calculation
rules as I said different calculation
rules. What is minimum uh threshold?
What is withholding tax amount when it
will be paid on invoice on a payment. So
I have two options and then you have
accounts you want to set up. Um then you
have this um uh tax report uh number
series. You need to configure revenue
and uh uh purchase withholding tax
account and segments on the end. What is
important because before I start to work
it will not be enabled by default. You
need to go to general ledger setup
and to enable withholding tax and around
payment uh amount withholding tax if you
want to around payments. So this is
minimum this field is required. So you
need to set up minimum this one. And
after that you can start working. So now
I can choose for example this one vendor
and my lamp. And now let's say I have
100 quantity.
And if I look in a preview posting,
you will see I have withholding tax
entry included.
Okay, I can post it.
I can open and again if I go to find
entries, you will see withholding tax
entry. And what you will find here in
withholding tax entries because now we
have new entries. We have 5,000 and a
base. This is amount I uh I had because
uh price was 50 and 20% of that is
1,000. So I have withholding tax
calculation type normal withhold
because I configured this one not to use
payments. So everything is there. So
there is nothing in unrealized because I
use invoice model here. But now if I go
back and if I create new one
with the payments
because I have another item configured.
Yes, this one.
So if I say okay
100. So I have something in a posting
preview.
You will see here that I have base an
amount empty
and I have in unrealized
amount is 5,000
and uh remaining un unrealized amount is
the same because I do not pay anything
and unrealized based in 25,000. This is
what we got there. So this is now
unrealized because I am using option on
payment. But what else we have here? I
have specific fields withholding tax
absorb base. So if for some reason I
need to pay on a bigger amount
million whatever I can use this option
and if I look into preview posting
you will see that now system do not use
this 25,000 as a base but it used
million as a base. If so that means if
there is any reason you want to use
different model you can do it. This is
not a problem. So you can decide okay
regardless what what I have from this
invoice I need to have calculation based
on another amount. So it will just
override um invoice on on invoice amount
will be the same but it will be override
basis for calculation. So I will just
delete it because I don't need it. And
when I post
again if I find entries
as I already show I have now unrealized
entries. Now when I pay this and I close
this amounts it will uh be removed from
unrealized to realized amount. So this
is let's say short demo about
withholding tax. Uh what else I wanted
to show
uh behind demo? Yes, when you post we
have entries but some limitations
as I said in the beginning only with
purchase process. So currently we do not
cover other options. So no employee not
customers only purchase process. Um this
is enabled as a global app. So this is
available everywhere. This everywhere is
except these four countries you for
localization you can you can find uh on
this screen Australia, New Zealand,
India and Italy. I will explain about
that but with no localization. So
regardless if you are UK, US, Germany,
any countries you will get the same
functionality no localization for any
specific country in this moment. Why we
have these four countries outside of
that? because they already have
withholding tax in somehow in all these
four countries and Australia, New
Zealand actually they have almost
absolutely the same because this holding
tax you could just see is almost the
same what we have in Australia New
Zealand. So this is NZ B app idea is
that in next release we will enable
through feature management upgrade
process so they can remove from existing
model they have right now in outside in
New Zealand. So this is what will come
next and they can switch to new model uh
with new model again with some
localizations on top of that because in
outside New Zealand we have localization
so they will get some localization on
top of that. So this is why this upgrade
will come later. But again even with
this upgrade they will get absolutely
the same level functionalities. We still
highly suggest once we've enabled this
upgrade to switch to new model because
we will continue to invest into new
model. So if you want to get much more
from withholding taxes it will be better
to use new model and not old one. In
Italy we have completely different
withholding tax. So it will be subject
of research what we need to do how we
can and where we can enable new model
and the same for India. So this is right
now uh limit a set of limitations. So
you cannot enable in these four
countries but in all other countries
regarding if Microsoft localization or
partner localizations you can use
withholding tax without any issue. You
can see and you can find a lot of
general business central resources on
this page. So use one of these links to
find everything what you are interesting
for. You can subscribe on our LinkedIn
page to find all interesting updates
from our side and of course Business
Center YouTube channel. So thank you for
watching this video and thank you for
enjoying testing this new functionality.